A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence, miscellaneous 1938-1939 (Box 383)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence of the period, including personal letter: Letter from Senator Harry F. Byrd stating that he enjoyed a chat with Carter Glass; Letter from Alva B. Adams, chairman of the Public Lands and Surveys Committee, thanking Carter Glass for congratulatory note on his re-election; Letter from Carter Glass to Harry F. Byrd in which he states, "This whole New Deal program simply amounts to political corruption by misuse of taxpayers money"; Important letter from Carter Glass to Leo Crowley of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, roundly criticizing Marriner Eccles about a proposed reorganization of the banking system; Letters remarking about the attack made by Carter Glass on Colonel House in his book; a copy of an article on distribution of income reprinted from the Quarterly Journal of Economics, sent by the General Motors Corporation, whose employee wrote the article; Statement regarding the connection of Carter Glass with the attempt to make Woodrow Wilson the first president of the University of Virginia. (See envelope in this box); Expression of the idea by Carter Glass that Huey Long was the one responsible for the idea of curtailing production so as to raise prices, thereby ending a depression. Long's statement on cotton production cited. Carter Glass records opposition to the policy, which was later adopted. He opposed the AAA and National Recovery Administration; Telegram from the Secretary of the Senate, September 13, 1939, informing Carter Glass of the calling of an extra session of Congress; Copy of a Franklin D. Roosevelt speech promising to stop deficit financing, sent to Carter Glass by a bitter insurance executive; Letter blaming bankers attitudes for the withholding of money from circulation. Carter Glass responds that the reason is that "no one knows today what his dollar will be worth tomorrow"; List of the accomplishments of the public works projects of the federal government in Virginia. Carter Glass answers that the taxpayers consent should have been gotten and the state should have done the work; Editorial supporting Senator George for renomination and listing Carter Glass as a truly loyal Democrat, opposing the "liberal" theories espoused by Franklin D. Roosevelt; Carter Glass, in answer to a letter, states that Governor Price of Virginia was one of the worst of governors; Preliminary expressions of doubt as to the advisability of a third term for Franklin D. Roosevelt; Twelve page paper by William F. Russell of Columbia University on communism and the way to meet its menace; Carter Glass states, in answer to a letter, that he opposed the 1938 Appropriations bill as being too large, although he was chairman of the Appropriations Committee; Letters opposing the granting of further powers to the Federal Home Loan Board, particularly in regard to the chartering of federal savings and loan associations; Request from the Union Trust Company of Maryland that changes be made in the plan of the Federal Reserve Board to end the practice of interlocking directorates; Letter from W. G. McAdoo, inquiring as to the advisability of moving his family to Charlottesville; Telegram of November 10, 1938, from Carter Glass congratulating Pat McCarron on his re-election to the Senate, and the Senator's expression of appreciation; In answer to a letter from James E. Palmer, Carter Glass favorably notes W. A. Scott's repudiation of the book by Garrison on Franklin D. Roosevelt, Wilson, et. al. Carter Glass also mentions many communications from Paul M. Warburg attributing to Carter Glass authorship of the Federal Reserve Act; Editorial citing Edmund Platt's attitude toward restraining credit early in 1929, while he was on the Federal Reserve Board and his subsequent opposition to the abandonment of the gold standard; Letter of December 2, 1938, from Edmund Platt, expressing his agreement with Carter Glass on the "gradual destruction of the Federal Reserve System " and recalling his attacks on "the monetary magicians"; Letter from Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, pointing out the failure of the Federal Reserve System to serve as a commercial system because of its cheap money policy and the devaluation of the dollar. It is also stated that a check on the cheap money policy might develop, if bank deposits continue to increase, while interest rates remain low, and capital accounts continue to be difficult to increase; Carter Glass replying that the Federal Reserve System is being ruined by the presidential appointee at the head of the Board into a central bank is noted; Letter, November 17, 1938, to James E. Palmer, in which Carter Glass recalls having denounced the author, Garrison, but search of his records failed to reveal the attack; Correspondence by which Carter Glass forces correction of a newspaper story, stating that he Palmer biography of him was "authorized" by Carter Glass; Letter from Edmund Platt, citing a report by George W. Dowrie favoring the extension of branch banking even in opposition to state laws. Edmund Platt agrees with Dowrie and feels that Carter Glass probably does too; Letter criticizing Federal Housing Administration methods of rejecting an applicant as a credit risk and suggesting limitation of the powers of Federal Housing Administration authorities; Letter from A. Willis Robertson, a member of the House of Representatives, to Carter Glass, concerning appropriations for the Blue Ridge Parkway; Letters relating to the biographies being prepared simultaneously by Palmer and Messrs. Smith and Beasley, including letters from Carter Glass to Rixey Smith, while he was working on the collection here being examined. ( Carter Glass states that he never listened to lobbyists); Letter from Rixey Smith approving the condemnation of Harold L. Ickes by Carter Glass, after Harold L. Ickes attack; a letter expressing the opinion that the result of unemployment compensation grants is to encourage idleness is answered by Carter Glass with a statement of the stupidity of a government agency attempting to control the affairs of private business. Carter Glass recommends the abolition of the New Deal agencies; Correspondence congratulating Millard E. Tydings on his victory against administration forces in winning re-election to the Senate; Address "Recent Economic Trends," by Representative Woodrum, July 6, 1938.
- Correspondence on legislation 1940 (Box 384)
  A. Letters, telegrams, etc. in regard to legislation under consideration at the time: Letters relating to proposed amendments to the National Labor Relations Act; Opposition expressed to LaFollette bill; Correspondence giving views on the situation in Europe; Aid to Allies favored; Favor expressed for Walter-Logan bill by many correspondents; Opposition expressed to attempt to give the government title to submerged land off the coast; Repeal of the Johnson Act requested; Opposition to the Wheeler-Jones bill; Support for the Maloney bill, relating to the sugar industry asked; Aid for Poland supported; Support asked for the Gillette-Kleberg bill; Opposition to a bill permitting the establishment of branch banks across state lines; Letter from Stewart McDonald, Federal Housing Administration administrator, reporting on the work of his agency in Virginia during 1939; Letters opposing proposed changes in the organization of the Works Progress Administration; Approval expressed of the Barden amendments to the Wage-Hour Law; Favor expressed for the bill in the House to restrain chain stores in their exertion of monopoly powers; Report of the Senate Commerce Committee on the River and Harbor bill, April 3, 1940.
- Correspondence on legislation 1940 (Box 385)
  A. Letters, telegrams, etc. dealing with legislative matters under consideration: Letters urging careful consideration to the war situation in Europe, repeal of the Johnson and Neutrality Acts requested; Letters supporting Carter Glass stand in favor of sending supplies to the Allies to combat German aggression; Letters expressing opposition to the LaFollette Civil Liberties Bill; Letter from the president of the Dairymen's League, favoring legislation encouraging a sound credit system (reasonable level of prices) rather than a lowering of interest rates; Letter protesting the statement of the Department of Labor that lumber retailers were wholesalers; Letters, pro and con, concerning the Smith amendments to the Wagner Labor Relations Act; Letters and statements relating to the National Economy League, strongly opposing continued expenditures for luxury items by the government, if defense expenses continued; Many letters suggesting that Congress remain in session in order to provide for the nation's defense; Letter, June 14, 1940, from M. F. Brennan, president of the United Mine Workers, opposing the Smith amendment; Letters encouraging the continuation of freight forwarding services; Letter to Carter Glass from the chairman of the House Rules Committee, enclosing a copy of a letter from Representative Hoffman to his Republican colleagues attacking President Franklin D. Roosevelt; Requests for support of the Truman-Hobbes bill on transportation; Telegrams, May 16, 1940, requesting support for the President's talk on defense; Letters opposing the Jones-Wheeler bill; Questions raised in regard to a proposed law as to whether certain investments of trust companies would be exempt from specific regulations. Changes proposed; Question from a Democrat as to how to vote in 1940, if he could not support a further administration spending program; Letter from a clearing house association opposing the establishment of branch banks across state lines; Requests that the Truman-Hobbes bill be passed over the President's veto; Three petitions urging opposition to the Lee bill; Suggestion of a retail sales tax made by a lawyer; Letters, May, 1940, asking that Works Progress Administration workers not be reclassified and paid less; Correspondence from industrial concerns opposing the LaFollette bill; Support requested for the Logan-Walter bill; Form letter to the Senators from James M. Meade of the Commerce Committee, suggesting an amendment to the Federal Reserve Act which would be designed to enlarge the credit opportunities for small businesses; Copy of Frederick A. Delano's proposal for a "sound economic monetary system for the United States " (8 pages) accompanied by a request for criticism; Letter from Senator Bilbo of the Agricultural and Forestry Committee with several enclosures relating to types of covering for bales of cotton.
- Correspondence (Box 386)
  A. Letter from Blakey, President of the National Bank of Burlington opposing giving Comptroller of the Currency power to pass on dividends of National Banks; a thesis "Win the War with Gold" by Marvin and Heath; Letter from Citizens Bank of Fairmount regarding banks with branches; Many letters opposing the Smith Bill amending National Recovery Administration (Wagner Act); Many letters opposing adjournment of Congress; Many letters urging help for Finland; Many letters urging help for Britain; Many letters of opposition to entering the war.
- Correspondence (Box 387)
  A. Harry F. Byrd reports on non-essential government spending of which Committee Carter Glass was a member and discusses monetary policy; Paper by Frederick A. Delano, an uncle of the President and later Comptroller of the Currency; Most items relate to national defense.
- Correspondence on legislation 1939-1940 (Box 388)
  A. Correspondence on various subject under legislative consideration at the time: Papers protesting further government infringement upon the life insurance business; Letter protesting further shipments of materials to Japan, which aid her in the war against China; Pleas to insure the retaining of a 3 1/2% interest rate on mortgages held by the Federal Land Banks; Letter from a banker, having to do with bank loans to officers; Aid to Finland requested; Letter questioning the possibility of a repudiation of the national debt; Letters supporting or expressing opposition to proposed changes in the Wage and Hour Law; Suggested amendments to the Fair Labor Standard Act; pamphlet stating reasons for opposing the St. Lawrence Seaway; Suggestion from Illinois Manufacturers' Association that the National Labor Relations Act be repealed, or at least changed in stated respects.
- Correspondence on legislation (Box 389)
  A. List of the ideas of the Transportation Association of America, concerning governmental policies toward the railroads; Letters concerning excise taxes on tobacco; Expression of opposition to the proposed Federal Mine Inspection Bill; Letters expressing appreciation to Carter Glass for introducing a bill in the Senate against interlocking bank directorates' Pamphlet concerning dentistry and the National Health Program; Letter from the Campana Sales Company, protesting a demand by the Federal Trade Commission for information concerning the financial operations of the business; Letters favoring the Wheeler-Truman bill, concerning transportation; Letter, January 24, 1940, protesting the unreasonably high capital requirements for banks which are members of the Federal Reserve System and also want to establish branches; Letter favoring the Kindergarten Bill; Cotton interests request extension of the Reciprocal Trade Agreements; Letter from a member bank of the Federal Reserve System, criticizing the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation for taking so long to answer vital correspondence; Letters and telegrams, concerning a British embargo on American tobacco, including communications from Cordell Hull at the Department of State; Copy of a bill from the Senate Commerce Committee, regarding public works projects on rivers and harbors; Letter enclosing a statement entered in the Congressional Record by Senator Harry F. Byrd, dealing in excellent fashion with the low rate of interest on government bonds and its effects; Letters opposing the quota system for states under civil service laws; Letter from a Winchester, Virginia, bank, stating that, contrary to prevalent opinion, there was no lack of credit facilities in 1939.
- Correspondence (Box 390)
  A. Letters relative to loan to Finland; Japanese aggression in China; Advertising of liquor by radio.
- Correspondence on legislation 1940 (Box 391)
  A. Miscellaneous letters, 1940: Letters from a coal mining and shipping firm, relating to proper pricing of coal; Letters opposing the use of radio for liquor advertisements; Letter favoring the exemption of dairy products from compliance with the Federal Wage Hour Law; Letter opposing the continued application of the Reciprocal Trade Agreement to the manganese industry; Attacks on the methods employed in taking the census; Protests concerning the delay in proceeding with the taking of the census; Letter favoring the bill presented by Senator Logan to limit the powers of Federal bureaus; Letter opposing price supports for sugar beet growers; Copy of a resolution by the West Virginia Chamber of Commerce, expressing opposition to the Mead bill, which would set up an Industrial Loan Corporation; Letters requesting continued protection for he sugar industry; Letter stating that gold was being substituted for credit as reserves and that ineligible paper was being discounted; Letter from Blythe W. Branch to Dr. Douglas S. Freeman, March 15, 1940, warning of the danger to America of continued German aggression; Warning of impending danger to America of the fall of Finland; Letters criticizing the Wagner Act and the Fair Labor Standard Act, advocating changes; Letters, pro and con, on legislation to restrain chain store organization; Letter suggesting that more strict mine inspection is intended to do more than insure health and safety; Letter from the Association of Ship Brokers and Agents, opposing the grant of power over coastal waterways to the Interstate Commerce Commission; Letters favoring the maintenance of an independent banking system in preference to a system of branch banking; Editorial in the Columbus Evening Dispatch, April 11, 1940, showing how federal agencies, once established, extend their powers, e. g., the S. E. C.; Memorandum from the Federal Advisory Council advising against adoption of amendments to the Federal Home Loans Bank Act; Letter from Representative Bierman, April 4, 1940, concerning responsibility for the establishment of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation; Letter, April 3, 1940, from Senator Downey, asking Carter Glass to be present when he criticizes the Social Security Act. He said public funds were going to wealthy people, instead of contributions going to needy folks; Letters in regard to amendments to the National Labor Relations Act; Banker opposition to Jones-Wheeler bill; Reports, March 15, 1940, concerning rivers and harbors; Letters relating to the Hull reciprocal trade program; Letter from a farmer, requesting more liberal loan conditions and an extension of parity price plans.
- Political correspondence 1940-1942 (Box 392)
  A. Labor legislation: Petitions opposing all anti-labor legislation which were under consideration, e. g., the Smith bill; Several letters having to do with the decision of the War Labor Board in the case involving the Walker-Turner company; Letters specifically favoring or opposing the forty-hour week, the closed shop, overtime pay, etc.; Letters protesting the advantages enjoyed by a laborer over a white-collar worker; Letters opposing the St. Lawrence Seaway project; Brief of a case before the Supreme Court, concerning the forty-hour week and overtime wages.
  B. Correspondence between Rixey Smith and the company which published the biography of Carter Glass by Smith and Norman Beaseley.
  C. Correspondence with Henry Morgenthau, Secretary of the Treasury, including notes from the secretary thanking Carter Glass for supporting certain legislation, for example, continuation of the presidential power to devalue the dollar.
  D. Correspondence concerning the attempt of William H. Peters to be reimbursed by the government for damages done to his family during the Civil War. Carter Glass expressed the opinion that introduction of such a bill would be fruitless.
- Correspondence on federal judgeships 1940-1943 (Box 393)
  A. Correspondence concerning persons eligible to fill vacant offices, particularly the position of Judge of the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Virginia: Letter of recommendation to Carter Glass; Carter Glass' recommendations.
- Correspondence on politics and legislation 1939-1940 (Box 394)
  A. Copies of reports submitted top the Board of Overseers of Sweet Briar College, of which Carter Glass was a member.
  B. Correspondence concerning the possibility of constructing a large apartment house next to the Arlington Cemetery, rather than enlarging the cemetery, including a letter from President Franklin D. Roosevelt on the subject.
  C. Correspondence relating to the Thomas Jefferson Bicentennial Commission, of which Carter Glass was Chairman; Letter from Howard Smith.
  D. Items of correspondence concerning the possible repeal of the poll tax as a prerequisite, something which Carter Glass opposed.
  E. Miscellaneous correspondence having to do largely with the recommending of people for jobs: Letters from Henry L. Stimson, Secretary of War, are included; Letter, February 25, 1941, expressing opposition to a change in reserve requirements designed to make it more difficult for the government to borrow from the Federal Reserve System; Small pamphlet concerning the excess profits tax.
  F. Miscellaneous letters relating mostly to aid for England; Picture of Mr. and Mrs. Carter Glass.
- Correspondence (Box 395)
  A. Letters urging Carter Glass to support Wendell Wilkie to office; Protests against the booing of Carter Glass' references to Jefferson in a speech in Chicago; papers indicating great fear of New Deal and Franklin Delano Roosevelt; Great unrest in the country; Letters urging Carter Glass to put the country above party; Letters from across the country urging Carter Glass to put country above party.
- Correspondence on legislation 1941-1942 (Box 396)
  A. Correspondence: Letters dealing with the proposed Longshoreman's and Harbor Worker's Compensation Act, mostly opposing the enactment of the legislation; Requests for support of the Murdock-Gillette Bill, S.1861; Suggestion, from Anchorage, Alaska, for the impeachment of the President, if he sent the Navy to the aid of the British; Other such suggestions; Letter stating opposition of the automobile dealers of Danville, Virginia, to a more strict Regulation; Other such letters; Numerous letters and telegrams suggesting legislation prohibiting the calling of strikes in industries vital to the defense program; Numerous letters asking for support for a measure affording a 15% pay raise for all postal employees; Letters expressing opposition to the St. Lawrence Seaway plan; a brief description of a possible Continental Defense Force, submitted by the American Legion at Norfolk; Numerous telegrams and letters pro and con over the Smith anti-strike bill, which Carter Glass favored; Pledges of support from various sources after December 7, 1941, for instance, an assurance of continuous war production from the National Association of Manufacturers; Letters and telegrams urge the adoption of price control legislation and rent controls; Letter enclosing an editorial from the Chicago Daily Tribune, December 4, 1941, stating that price controls were not yet needed, because of the limitations which would be placed on supply; Letter suggesting that Congress assert its authority over the President and enclosing two articles by Westbrook Pegler on the subject; Letter, December 4, 1941, from the representatives of the United Federal Workers of America, favoring price control while opposing wage-fixing; Telegram suggesting improvement in wording for the Lanham bill concerning defense housing, accompanied by a copy of the bill and a report by Lanham; Letters opposing the closed shop; Letter from the Gary, Indiana, Chamber of Commerce, favoring the St. Lawrence Seaway project; Form letter, November 28, 1941, from Woliam Green, president of the American Federation of Labor, opposing proposed anti-strike legislation; Suggestion to the Secretary of the Treasury, Henry Morgenthau, that a tax on increases in income be levied, so that people not employed in defense industries would not be penalized.
- Correspondence on banking legislation 1933 (Box 397)
  A. Approximately 100 letters from all over the country, most of which were written in March, 1933, suggesting possible courses of action to meet the problems which caused the bank holiday, including guarantee of deposits and branch banking: Eight-page pamphlet by J. R. Edwards, "The Contamination of Credit"; Notes concerning the selling of preferred stock by banks to meet emergency needs sent to Carter Glass by Robert V. Fleming, President of Riggs National Bank; Twelve-page booklet, "Some ABC's of Currency Inflation," sent to Carter Glass by Edmund E. Lincoln, who had the advice of H. Parker Willis on the contents of the booklet; Letter from Walter Nesbit, a member of the House of Representatives, enclosing a letter from the Treasurer of the State of Illinois concerning the adverse effect on state funds of terminating the payment of interest on demand deposits; Digest of the Emergency Bank Bill of March, 1933, prepared by Charles W. Collins, sent to Carter Glass for his records by Gardner B. Perry, including lists of the emergency and permanent provisions of the bill.
- Political correspondence 1938-1946 (Box 398)